Artifacts Collection 0016.123.001
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
Artifacts
Bulk, 1850-1950
1800-1982
0016.123.001
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
35.0 Cubic feet 7 Boxes, Films, oversized boxes, objects
Beizer, Jacob, Policeman; Ellis, Robert; Fisher, Annie; Harris, Victor; Kashmann, Benjamin, Meat dealer, 1881-1954, Hartford, CT; Kone, Samuel C., Real Estate broker, 10/18/1880-02/02/1951, Russia; Ribicoff, Abraham, Politician, U.S. Senator, 04/9/1910 - 02/22/1998, New Britian, CT; Tabatsky, Abraham; Tucker, Sophie, Entertainer, (Sophie Kalish Abuza Tucker ), 1889 - 2/11/1966, Russia; Barnard-Brown Schools; Exhibits/ Annie Fisher; Finkelstein's Shoe Store; Haggadah; Hebrew Home and Hospital; Kashmann's Furniture Store; Knights of Pythias; Organizations; Politics; Religious objects; Teffilin; Tucker, Sophie; War Veterans; Yale University
- Unboxed
  - Shofar picture, undated
  - Child's tallit, undated
  - Tzedakah boxes/ Yeshiva of Hartford donate by Ida Ginsberg, undated
  - Tzedakah boxes/ Palestine Orphanage donate by Edna Shain Farber, undated
  - South end Hebrew women's Talmud torah, undated
  - B'nai Brith Ararat Lodge cup dated, undated
  - Kiddush cup from J. Koplowitz golden wedding, undated
  - 2 High Holiday, Rosh Hashanah, pictures donated b Irene Tabatsky, 1896
  - Haggadah, c. 1896, donated by Hebrew Home, undated
  - 1 Wedgwood (light blue) covered candy dish, undated
  - 1 teapot with sugar and creamer, undated
  - 3 prayer books for World War II Servicemen, undated
  - Wooden nickel, 1918
  - Jewish War rally Banner, 1918, 1942
  - Red cross book donor's card, 1942, undated
  - Max Yaffe award ad booklet, moved to JWV artifact box, undated
  - Israeli key ring, undated
  - Oil lamp, undated
  - Pitcher from Israel, undated
- Army Uniforms
  - Midrasha banner and two t-shirts, undated
- Badges, Pins, Buttons, Medals & Ribbons
  - Army uniform worn and donated by Muriel Phillips Engleman, undated
  - Agudas Achim medals (2), 1915
    AvRutick, Abraham, Rabbi, Russia; Agudas Achim
  - Brown School lapel pin, 1915 (belonged to North, Rose Rater - mother of Paula Smith), undated
  - Charter Oak enamel pin (donated by H. Funkenstein), undated
  - Council of Jewish Women button, 1908
  - Dedication ribbon of Buckley Bridge 1908 with gold-plated medallion, (donated by Selma Schwartz), undated
  - Emanuel Synagogue Religious School Award pin, 1930
  - Florence Nightingale club pin, c. 1930, undated
  - Free Soviet Jews button, 1974
  - Greater Hartford Baseball League 1974, 1976 buttons (2), undated
  - Hebrew Home & Hospital Large Button Pin ("Love is Ageless"), 1986
  - Hebrew Home & Hospital Large Button Pin, 1986 Groundbreaking (w/ green ribbon), undated
  - Hebrew Home & Hospital Small Button Pin, (teal blue, "Keep the Promise" -- created for Abrahms Blvd. facility fundraising), 1920
  - Health Commisioner Badge 1920-1923 (belonged to Kashman, Benjamin), undated
  - Hartford Alderman Third Ward badge (belonged to Ellis, Robert I.), 1978
  - Israel Independence, 30th Anniversary button, 1978, (donated by Phyllis Wachspress), 1920s
  - Jewish National Fund Button 1920s, w/ light blue and white ribbon, 1906
  - John Hay Lodge Medal, 1906 [see Artifacts/Organizations box for accompanied certifiicates), undated
  - Kone, Samuel Medals (5) and Ribbons (2) -- (inc. Jewish Consumptives Relief Society, Knignts of Pythias, Independent Order of B'rith Abraham), 1990s
  - Life Member Hartford Yeshiva lapel/hat pin, 1990s, 1917
  - Military Census, 1917 Badge with Ribbon (Local Board, 3rd District), undated
  - Mount Sinai Hospical Auxiliary lapel pin, 1919
  - Municipal Celebration, 1919 Committee Badge w/ ribbon (red, white, blue), 1950
  - Retired Policeman badge Hartford, 1950 (belonged to Beizer, Jacob), undated
  - Square dancing badge belonging to Lillian and Vic Harriet, undated
  - Star of David button, 1933
  - Yale button, 1933 (belonged to Vic Harris), undated
  - Joint Distribution Committee Conference, Philadelphia, 1925 (belonged to J. Hoffenberg), undated
  - Businesses Artifacts
    - Children's curlers made from scups of leather by farmer in Colchester for extra income, undated
    - Crown Market bottle caps (2), undated
    - Davidson and Leventhal (D & L) charge card (Mrs. Edward Lotstein), undated
    - Davidson and Leventhal (D & L) plastic shopping bag (blue and gray 17" x 13"), 1930
    - Farmer's Egg Scale, 1930's?, 1915
    - Finkelstein's Shoe Store - Shoe horn c. 1915 (donated by Ada and Jennie Wald), undated
    - G. Fox gift box (9 1/2" x 9 1/2", red), undated
    - G. Fox gift box (17" x 13", mauve), undated
    - G. Fox gift box (6" x 6" x 2", ivory with G. Fox lettering in script), undated
    - G. Fox merchandise (Hane's pantyhose in new packaging with labeled price), undated
    - G. Fox paper bag (9 1/2" x 7 1/2", mauve), undated
    - G. Fox price tags, 1920s
    - Haddad's Linen Store receipt (1920s) with G. Fox tag affixed, undated
    - Kashmann's promotional items -- button advertisement, hearts, undated
    - Kashmann's wooden pictoral advertisement plague (donated by Marjorie Walton), undated
    - L.B. Haas & Company (tobacco) medallion commemorating business 1955-1953, undated
    - Marlow's Inc. 50th Anniversary pot holder (gold with lettering), undated
    - Marlow's Inc. Shopping bag (white with red lettering "Marlow for Everything"), 1915
    - Peddler license 1915, donate by Mr. and Mrs. Jack Paul, undated
    - Peddler license badge, NYC #19772 (belonging to Jack Paul's father), undated
    - Savitt shopping bag, large with red and yellow lettering - "POMG", 1850
    - Tailor's Thimble c.1850, undated
- Wedding Dresses
  - Bertha Seide Cohan's wedding dress, undated
- Ceramic and Glass
  - Title & Rich Fashion Shop cloth pictograph mounted on wooden plaque, undated
  - Afula Municipality, Israel china plate, 1915
  - Advertising plates (2) of Nathan Baggish bakery c. 1915, (donated by Mrs. Morris Weiss), undated
  - Ceramic mugs (w/ broken handles and designations) (donated by daughters of Joseph B. and Lizzie Yael), undated
  - Commemorative plate, 20th anniversary of Rabbi P. Lazowsky, 1974, undated
  - Promotional Mug "Smirnoff mule", (copper-plated), undated
  - Shaving Mug/ Samuel Hartman, undated
  - Shaving Mug/ Isaac Kashman, 1923
  - Silver Loving Cup, 1923 (YMHA to Daniel C. Melrose), undated
  - Wine Decanters (3, clear glass), undated
- Commemorations
  - Yellin Saloon, small glasses (2), undated
  - Citation of Honor (framed), Dr. Morris Cohen (from JHSGH), undated
  - Citation of Honor (plaque), Herman P. Kopplemann (from Emanual Synagogue), undated
  - Doorplates, (metal-plated) (3) for JHSGH exhibits, undated
  - Exhibit plate (brass) presented by the Hartford Hebrew Women's Aid Society, undated
- Desk Embossers, Seals, and Offical Stamps
  - Sabbat plates, decorative [1 ceramic, metal/enamel plated], 1917
  - Ados Israel, 1917, undated
  - Aladdin Shop -- office stamps from c. 1930 (donated by Emma Cohen), undated
  - Hebrew Ladies Free Loan Association office stamp c. 1900 (donated by Rabbi Avigdor), undated
  - New Britain federation Seal, undated
- Fox Family/Lewis Fox
  - Shoor foundation seal, undated
  - American Flags (2), undated
  - Award plates dedicated to Lewis Fox (3), undated
  - Bible, undated
  - Black and orange knit tie (Princeton related), undated
  - Brass and enamel breast plate for Torah scroll, undated
  - Cap with initials "A.H.C." (Asylum Hill Cadets), undated
  - Ceremonial hood and gown worn by Lewis Fox at reception of honorary doctoral degree, undated
  - Felt armband with initials "NWS" (Noah Webster School), undated
  - Four pennnants labeled: Camp Greylock, Clio, Camp Wigwam, and Princeton, undated
  - Honor Society plaque awarded to Beatrice Auerbach, 1977
  - H.P.H.S. Yearbook, 1977
  - Large felt banner labeled "Princeton 1926", undated
  - Leather three-ring binder, undated
  - Music book of Miriam Stern Fox, undated
- Garments & Fashion Accessories
  - Sewing kit of Miriam Stern Fox, undated
  - Feather used by Sophie Tucker, undated
  - Annie fisher purse fan and handkerchief case donated by Mr. and Mrs. R. Bagley, undated
  - Russian boot donate by Natalie Ziplow, 1850s
  - Shawl (1850s, black) donated by Ruth and Jack Sacks, undated
  - Elbert Weinberg's dress (white), undated
  - Crocheted sign Jewish Historical Society made and donated by Doris Hurwitz, 1982, undated
  - Elbert Weinberg's dress, undated
- Matzah Covers
  - Women's Night cap donated by Beatrice Sisk, undated
- Organizations
  - Hand-made matzah cover, donated by Denese Mann, undated
  - Hebrew Women's Home for Children, foundation laying trowel 1928, undated
  - Jewish Center, Asylum Avenue, mezzuzah (set in glass plate), 1906
  - John Hay Lodge certificates, Knights of Pythias,1906 (2) (donated by Isaac Missal;s family) -- [see badges/pin/medals box for accompanied medal], undated
  - Judith Lodge #33 Independent Order of the Free Sons of Israel, organized 1871 wooden gavel, 1948
  - Mt Sinai Hospital, foundation laying trowel, 1948, 1912
  - Talmud Torah 1912 cornerstone box (metal), undated
  - Tzedakah boxes/ Jewish Children's Service Organization (JCSO), 1915-1920, undated
- Personal Artifacts, Miscellaneous
  - Tzedakah boxes/ Yeshiva of Hartford (donated by Arline Wolansky), undated
  - Button hook of S. H. Rosenthal, 1900s
  - Eyeglasses, 1900s in Gold frame belonged to David Abramovitz, donated by Irene Tabatsky, 1910
  - Hat Pins, 1910 (2) (12" long w/ jeweled tops) donated by Esther Slavkin, undated
  - Lead dreidle made by father of Dr. Morris Cohen, donated by Seth Brown, undated
  - Military Dogtags (belonged to Rosker, Esther), 1930s
  - Medicine container (tin w/ lining), German c. 1930s, undated
  - Mortar & Pestle, c. late 1800's, Germany, 1916
  - Mother's Day card, 1916, undated
  - Olive wood gavel, gift from Israel (gift of Sam Kellin, 1969), undated
  - Ten Commandments written head of a pin, donate by Flora Kaplan Dublin, undated
- Politics
  - Weaver High School Diploma (belonged to Rosker, Esther), undated
  - Campaign button; Gloria Schaffer, U. S. Senate, undated
  - Campaign button; Abe/ Abraham Ribicoff, undated
  - Campaign buttons; Abe '74, Jerry Wagner (Senate), Joe Lieberman (Senate), 1974
- Religious/Ritual Objects [synagogue related]
  - Oversized -- Abe Ribicoff plastic shopping bag, 1974, undated
  - Agudas Achim commemorative print block plate (Memorial Service), 1928
  - Agudas Achim groundbreaking trowel, 1928 [given to Barney Wachtel], undated
  - Agudas Achim Skull Caps (2) (commemorating Diamond Jubilee 1881-1962), undated
  - Anniversary plate (clear glass), 50th, Emmanuel Synagogue, undated
  - Challah cover, undated
  - Door handle, Florence Street synagogue, undated
  - Haggadah of Passover, scroll, undated
  - "Keren Ami" box donated by Shirley Seltzer, 1800s
  - Kippah, early 1800s from Vilna, undated
  - Kippah, 18th Annual Testimonial Dinner Congregation Teferes Israel, 1974 in honor of Rabbi Haskel Lindenthal, 1900
  - Kippots, c. 1900 (3) from Chesterfield, CT synagogue (donated by Ben Schwab), undated
  - Matzo cover (hand-embroidered) and Passover Saltcellar (donated by Mrs. Michael Fleisher), undated
  - Matzo cover (cloth/powder blue), undated
  - Matzo cover (green w/ hand embroidery) of Florence Welk Marder, donated by Sarah Plen, undated
  - Skullcap (white), Connecticut Orthodox Youth Conference, 1800s
  - Skullcap from Eastern Europe early 1800s, undated
  - Skullcap [rose colored, unidentified], 1860
- Small Books, Ledgers, and Journals
  - Wimpel of William Rothschild c. 1860 donated by Sam Hoffenberg, undated
  - Annie Fisher Bible (donated by Eleanor Bagley), 1883
  - Autograph Album 1883-1886 (owned by Knock, Adeline), undated
  - "Daniel Deronda" by George Eliot, 2 vols. given to Cantor Israel Tabatsky on Bar Mitvah, 1850
  - Gelb's Hartford City Directory, 1850 (donated by Bea Hirschberg, 1995), undated
  - Genesis, English translation (belonged to M. Mancall), undated
  - Pharmaceutical Notebook of Samuel Maislen, 1938
  - Prayers/blessing book for Klein-Frankel Wedding 1938, 1855
  - Prayer book, c. 1855 donated by Mrs. Rose Weinberg, undated
  - Prayer books (2) of Abraham Dubrow donated by Mr. and Mrs. Kurnitsky, undated
  - Rubiyat of Omer Kyam in Yiddish, donated by Sophie Botack Kellin, 1848
  - Siddur, Book of Psalms 1848, 1932
- Tefellin & Tallis Bags
  - Upsilon Lambda Phi Fraternity Directory, 1932, 1920
  - Tallis bag, 1920s/ Suisman, Michael, 1950
  - Tallis bag, 1950s/ Sudarsky, Michael, undated
  - Hand-embroidered tallit bag (black) (donated by Mrs. Michael Fleisher), undated
  - Tefellin in bag of Pichus Baggish, grandfather (donated by P. Baggish, 1980), 1895
  - Tefillin bag, c. 1895 used by father of Harry Goldberg, 1905
  - Tefillin and bag 1905 wedding present, (donated by Morris Robbins) - two sets of Tefellin, undated
  - Hand-made tefillin bags c. 1850 one with tefillin (donated by Michael Sudarsky), undated
  - Tallit, large (donated by Harriet Katz), undated
  - 3 Tallit bags w/ tefillin [unidentified], 1883
- Film: On Shelf (Oversized)
  - Tallit in Bag of Dr. William Leichner (1883-1943), undated
  - 2011.01 "Jews in Early Hartford" 16mm film, release print, 1900
  - 2011.02 "About People: Jews of Hartford 1900-1925", 16mm film, 1953
  - 2011.03 "Mission to Israel", 16mm film, 1953-4, undated
  - 2011.04 "About People: Greater Hartford Section-NCJW Justice for Children", TV Panel, moderated by Norma Schatz, undated